Guide to the Eugene Marshall Papers, 1839-1962 RL.00850
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Eugene Marshall papers
1839-1962
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Marshall, Eugene, 1832-1919
RL.00850
5 Linear Feet
Farmer, banker, and Union Cavalry officer of Caledonia, Minnesota. Collection includes correspondence, diaries, writings, legal documents, printed material, record books, scrapbooks, and photographs, chiefly relating to Marshall's military service with Brackett's Battalion, Minnesota Cavalry, in Kentucky, Tennessee, and Alabama (1862-1864) and on the Northwest Indian expedition (1864-1865). Diaries include comments on his immigration from Brockton, MA to Minnesota in 1853, and on secessionist spirit in Texas, 1859-1860. Letters from his sister reflect impact of immigrants on Brockton, 1890-1910. Includes material documenting aspects of the Dakota Territory in the 1860s; Plains Indians; Red River carts; the impact of the Civil War on southern unionists, middle Tennessee, and African Americans; religion; education; the status of women; towns in southeastern New England, upper Middle West, Tennessee, and Mississippi River Valley; and Ignatius Donnelly, Horace Mann, and William T. Sherman.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Papers of Eugene Marshall were acquired by Duke University in 1960-1962.
Biographical Note
Eugene Marshall (1832-1919), born in North Bridgewater, Massachusetts, was a surveyor, farmer, and banker who served as a volunteer in the Union Army during the Civil War and Sioux Wars (1862-1865) while with units known successively as Curtis' Horse, the 5th Iowa Cavalry, and Brackett's Battalion. He married Elizabeth "Lizzie" Williams (1843-1895) in 1866 following his medical discharge from the Army. They had four children together: Ella Fannie (1868-1888), Hayward (1870-1923), Anna Olive (1876-1967), and Ethel Eugenia (1880-1958). Marshall left his family home early and spent most of his adult civilian life in Minnesota and Iowa, and his retirement years in Manchester, Tennessee. While on his travels in and out of uniform, he recorded a wealth of observations concerning the events, people, and environments in each area. Marshall supplemented his observations with accounts of his own participation in politics and economic endeavors, as well as commentary on national figures and events. His experiences in the Midwest and the South are complemented by letters from his sister who had remained in North Bridgewater.
Collection Overview
The papers of Eugene Marshall (1832-1919) span 1847-1962 and consist primarily of diaries kept by Marshall during his military service in the Civil and Sioux Wars and correspondence exchanged with his sister, Olive (Mrs. Frederick Trow). The collection is divided into the following series: the Diaries (1851-1895); Correspondence and other documents (1847-1918; 1958-1962); Writings, both printed and manuscript, including poetry, speeches, newspaper articles, and letters to the editor (1863-1918 and undated); Genealogy of Marshall and related families; Volumes and Scrapbooks (1858-1908); Photographs (1858-1913 and undated); and a small folder of miscellaneous material. There is also an oversize folder in the collection, which contains a certificate attesting to Marshall's membership in the Minnesota chapter of the Sons of the American Revolution. The collection also includes one of the Indian arrows that wounded Marshall during the campaign of 1864.
Voyages and travels; Alabama -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Texas -- Politics and government 1846-1865; Southern States -- Social conditions; Indians of North America -- Great Plains; Emigration and immigration -- United States; Kentucky -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel; Indians of North America -- Wars 1862-1865; Migration, Internal -- United States; Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Southern States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; United States. Army. Cavalry -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Description and travel; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Donnelly, Ignatius, 1831-1901; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859
- Information Folder (Box 1)
- Correspondence and other documents, 1847-1962 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, largely exchanged with his sister, Olive (Mrs. Frederick Trow); legal and business documents; printed materials (mostly related to veterans' reunions); and newspaper clippings (1858-1915). There is a small folder of miscellaneous material and an oversize certificate attesting to Marshall's membership in the Minnesota chapter of the Sons of the American Revolution.
  - Correspondence, 1847-1869 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1911 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1912-1962 and undated (Box 3)
  - Legal and business documents, 1855-1935 (Box 5)
  - Printed materials and ephemera, 1864-1915 (Box 5)
  - Clippings: 1815-1914, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 6, Oversize-folder 1)
- Diaries
  The diaries, 35 small volumes and related materials, contain information on Marshall's activities in the years 1851-1861, but are primarily devoted to his military service in the Civil and Sioux Wars (1861-1866). A typescript of a portion (1861, Nov. 20-1864, Mar. 14) of the war diary prepared by Marshall's daughter, Ethel, also forms part of the collection.
  Diaries have been individually labeled in chronological order. A guide correlating volume numbers to dates has been filed with them. In some instances, wear on the pencil entries has rendered some pages nearly illegible. Some effort has been made to provide reconstruction of the entries. Diary entries after 1866 are few and scattered - clustered around and primarily concerned with the illnesses and deaths of Marshall's wife and eldest daughter.
  - Guide to the Diaries (Box 3)
  - #1 1851 (Box 7)
  - #2 1852 (Box 7)
  - #3 1853 (Box 3)
  - #4 1859-1860 (Box 3)
  - #5 1857-1861 (Box 7)
  - #6 1859-1860 (Box 3)
  - #7 1861 (Box 3)
  - #8 1861 (Box 7)
  - #9 1862 (Box 3)
  - #10 1862 (Box 3)
  - #11 1862 (Box 3)
  - #12 1862 (Box 3)
  - #13 1862 (Box 3)
  - #14 1862 (Box 3)
  - #15 1862-1863 (Box 4)
  - #16 1852 (Box 7)
  - #17 1863 (Box 4)
  - #18 1863 (Box 4)
  - #19 1863 (Box 4)
  - #20 1863 (Box 4)
  - #21 1863-1864 (Box 4)
  - #21A 1863 (Box 4)
  - #22 1864 (Box 4)
  - #23 1864 (Box 4)
  - #24 1864 (Box 4)
  - #25 1864 (Box 4)
  - #25A 1864 (Box 4)
  - #26 1864 (Box 4)
  - #27 1864 (Box 4)
  - #28 1864 (Box 4)
  - #29 1864 (Box 4)
  - #30 1865 (Box 7)
  - #31 1865 (Box 7)
  - #32 1863-1865 (Box 7)
  - #33 1865-1866 (Box 4)
  - #34 1890 (Box 7)
  - #35 1895 (Box 5)
  - Typescript: 1862 Mar. 1 - Jun. 30 (Box 5)
  - Typescript: 1862: Mar. 1 - Oct. 10 (Box 5)
  - Bound transcript of diaries (Box 9)
- Writings
  Writings, both printed and manuscript, include poetry, speeches, newspaper articles, and letters to the editor (1863-1918 and undated).
  - Assorted published material, 1864-1897 and undated (Box 5)
  - Article on Civil War Experiences, Dec. 1861- Feb. 1862, in Manchester Times, July 1918 (Box 5)
  - Article on 1864 Expedition in St. Paul Press, Jan. 25, 1897 (Box 5)
  - Poetry, 1863-1914 (Box 5)
  - Typescripts: Poems: 1855, 1863, 1880s, and undated (Box 5)
  - Drafts: letters and and articles for St. Paul Press, 1864-1865 (Box 5)
  - Commentary on Reconstruction and the causes of the Civil War, 1865-1876 (Box 5)
  - Notes for Report on National Resources and Topography of Dakota Territory, ca. 1865 (Box 5)
  - Account of "The Great North Westerns Indian Expedition of 1864" (Box 5)
  - Reminiscences of George W. Northrup and related materials, 1898 (Box 5)
  - Commentary on Indian Policy (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical sketch (Box 5)
  - Typescripts: Sketch of History of Brackett's Battalion, Address to a Grand Army of the Republic Gathering (Box 5)
- Genealogy
  - Ancestry of Eugene Marshall (Box 5)
  - Ancestry of Olive Hayward (Box 5)
  - Ancestry of Francis Cooke (Box 5)
  - Genealogy of the Wild Family, 1897 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Volumes and Scrapbooks
  - Record of business and agricultural activity, 1858-1860, 1867 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook and ledger, 1857-1861, 1866-1867 (Box 8)
  - Ledger, 1906-1908 (Box 8)
  - Record book 1858-1860, 1867-1883 (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Eugene Marshall 1913 (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Eugene Marshall 1913 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Eugene (Elizabeth "Lizzie" Williams) Marshall ca. 1868-1880 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Eugene Marshall 1865 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Eugene Marshall and E.D. Peebles 1865 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Eugene Marshall and daughter Ethel (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Eugene Marshall's birthplace and boyhood home at Marshall's Corners, North Bridgewater Mass. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Haywood Marshall, Eugene Marshall's father (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photograph of arrow taken from Eugene Marshall's side after a fight with the Sioux Indians (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Eugene Marshall, cased tintype ca. 1865-1866 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Eugene Marshall, cased Daguerreotype ca. 1865-1866 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth Marshall, cased ambrotype (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1 empty case (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Eugene Marshall, tintype (undated) (Box 6)
  - Eugene Marshall, tintype (undated) (Box 6)
  - W.W. Williams, tintype, ca. 1858 (Box 6)
  - Copies of photographs (Box 6)
- Arrow, 1864 (Box 10)
  One of the Indian arrows that wounded Marshall during the campaign of 1864.